Today's דף daf is נח. Nun Chet. We start at the bottom
of נז עמוד ב Nun Zayin Amud Bet and we are finally
introducing what we sort of had said in the beginning of the
פרק perek but only once or twice alluded to, which is the
question about if an animal that's a טרפה trefa dies, in what
time frame does it die immediately or what? So we had mentioned
before the issue where there was some empirical evidence that the animal
did not die and the response was, oh, it must have died
within the year and that is sufficient for the status of a
טרפה. trefa. So now we're going to revisit that issue. So let's
take a look. It is eight lines from the bottom beginning of
the line נז עמוד ב. Nun Zayin Amud Bet.
אמר רב
הונא:
Amar Rav
Huna: סימן לטרפה יב חודש. siman le'trefa yud bet chodesh. A test
for something is a טרפה trefa is twelve months, which doesn't mean
that any animal that dies within twelve months was a טרפה, trefa,
might have died from other causes, but it means that if there
is a doubt that it's a טרפה trefa and it lives for
twelve months, then you will know that it is not a טרפה.
trefa. Okay, a טרפה trefa cannot live for twelve for more than
twelve months and then you can go ahead and שחט shacht this.
And then you can go ahead and שחט shacht this, that's important
in cases of ספק טרפה. safek trefa. Okay.
Now מיתיבי, meteiv, I'll ask you on this: סימן לטרפה כל שאינה
יולדת. siman le'trefa kol she'eina yoledet. We have a whole תוספתא Tosefta
here which has different ways of different assessments of how you know
something is a טרפה. trefa. Again, not how you know, I said
that wrong, because it doesn't mean that anything with this problem is
a טרפה. trefa. The תוספתא Tosefta points out there are a lot
of animals that can't give birth, either they're too old or that
they've had some type of fertility issue. So it's not that any
animal that can't give birth is a טרפה. trefa. So the way
of saying an indicator of a טרפה trefa is that it doesn't
give birth is a little imprecise. It really means, there must be
a technical scientific term for this, it must mean that when you
know it's a positive indicator, negative indicator, anyway, when it does give
birth you know it's not a טרפה. trefa. Okay,
so that is the first opinion. רבן גמליאל אומר: Rabban Gamliel omer:
No, משבחת והולכת בידוע שהיא כשירה. meshabbachas ve'holechet beyaduah she'hi keshaira. Here's
how you know: if there was some injury and you're not sure
if it's טרפה, trefa, if the animal's health starts improving after the
fact, so it's כשירה. keshaira. משתנבבת והולכת בידוע שהיא טרפה. misnavveves ve'holechet
beyaduah she'hi trefa. If it starts getting more ill and it's, you
know, its health is failing, בידוע שהיא טרפה, beyaduah she'hi trefa, you
know it's a טרפה. trefa. Now, he's not necessarily saying it will
die, which is interesting, and one does wonder these first two opinions,
if you'll remember going back to the beginning of the פרק, perek,
there was an opinion, although it got completely ignored, but there was
an opinion that a טרפה trefa can survive. So what makes something
a טרפה? trefa? I mean, because not all injuries and holes are
טרפות. trefot. So when you have these opinions, a טרפה trefa can't
give birth or a טרפה trefa gets sicker after the event, are
they saying these are indicators that the wound was fatal? That's one
way of understanding it, and in the end we all agree to
the principle or that a טרפה trefa won't live. But how do
you determine, you know, if you have a doubt whether the animal's
a טרפה? trefa? Well, see if it gives birth, see if it
starts getting better. Or maybe they don't agree to the principle that
it's about being fatal. Maybe they say with a certain type of
an injury, what type of an injury? An injury that causes it
to become infertile, an injury
that makes its health get worse rather than get better. The problem
with that, the second one you could certainly say, the problem with
the first one is we know, for example, the גמרא Gemara is
explicit that an animal with a missing womb is not a טרפה.
trefa. So it can't be any injury that leads to infertility. Okay,
so the simpler thing is to understand that we all agreed on
the principle that a טרפה trefa will die. The question is how
fatal, how soon, how to determine, and two ways here of determining
is: will it be able to give birth and will its health,
is its health getting better or worse? Now the גמרא Gemara goes
on,
רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, Rebbe said, and some have
the version רבי מאיר: Rebbe Meir: סימן לטרפה שלשים יום. siman le'trefa
shloshim yom. So thirty days, if it doesn't die within thirty days,
then you know it's not a טרפה. trefa.
It doesn't die or doesn't get better?
Doesn't die. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to Rebbe, והלא הרבה
מתקיימת שתים ושלש שנים? ve-lo harbeh miskayyemes shtayim ve-shalosh shanim? They said
to Rebbe, oh there are many that live two or three years.
So here again, actually interestingly, you are having the empirical evidence as
a contradiction. So this was a question: how could you say it's
twelve months? We have three opinions here, none of which gives twelve
months. Rebbe who gives a time gives a month, and the other
opinions don't give any particular timeframe at all. So where do you
get off saying, רב הונא, Rav Huna, that twelve months is
the
determiner?
Does an animal live three years? The animals don't have such long
lives. Right, and that's a long time. How could we say every
animal's going to die within
twelve months, within three years? Oh, well no, they said to Rebbe,
two or three years. They weren't saying that that's the timeframe. Maybe
that's why they would say don't go by a timeframe. Maybe they
would say go by the health improving. They would say go by
can it give birth. They're not saying you should use two or
three years, they're just saying you can't use a month if
animals can sometimes live after the. injuries two or three years, you
can't use a month as a basis of determining. Now your possibilities
maybe you should make it vary based on the animal, that's also
possible. But let's first get a response to how רב הונא Rav
Huna could say a year. So גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, tannai
hi, yeah, it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. We already know it's
a debate of תנאים, tannaim, but meaning we have yet another ברייתא
braita to bring. דתניא, detanya, we taught, ובגולגולת, u'vegulgoles,
when it comes to remember the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel
and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, if you have a skull, does it
cause טומאה tumah in a room, the טומאה tumah of a corpse?
And the answer is if there's a hole in the skull big
enough that a person couldn't live, then it doesn't represent the person
and it doesn't cause טומאה tumah in
the
room, טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel.
And the amount of a מקדח makdeach of an awl, so the
size of a hole of an awl. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebbi
Yosi, now that's not yet relevant to us, בן המשולם, Ben HaMeshullam,
מעשה ma'aseh באינבו, be'Invo,
there was a story in this place called אינבו Invo באחד שנפחת
גולגולתו, be'echad shenifchat gulgolto,
somebody that got a hole in his skull, ועשו לו חידוק של
קרויה, ve'asu lo chiduk shel kariya,
again here's some medical intervention which the גמרא Gemara feels is not
a challenge, meaning if somebody's a טרפה, treifah, medical intervention will not
help. The גמרא Gemara has said that consistently now a number of
times. Okay, so they made for him some type of a bandage
or some type of a, you know, thing which רש"י Rashi says
it's a dried out gourd, some hard thing to put over there
to fill up the hole, okay, what? Plaster. Oh, that's interesting. Okay.
וחיה, vechaya, and he lived! So you can't tell me that that
hole means that somebody won't live. So, okay, and how do you
say that that has הלכות halachos for either טומאה, tumah, טומאת אוהל,
tumas ohel, or as we are concerned for טרפה? treifah? So אמר
לו רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, amar lo Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar, משם
ראיה? misham raya? And the answer was, what, you want to prove
something from that? ימות החמה היה, yemos hachamah haya, that was the
summertime, דכיון דאתא עליו ימות הגשמים מיד מת, dekeivan de'asa alav yemos
hageshamim miyad mes, but after the end
by the end of the winter he had died. So some type
of injuries, and רש"י Rashi says the reverse is also true, some
type of injuries won't get exacerbated in certain seasons, but they will
in others. So the reason, says רש"י, Rashi, for the twelve months,
we're trying to give this a support for רב הונא Rav Huna
that says twelve months, is that, you know, anything that's a טרפה,
treifah, the person will definitely die when one of the seasons of
the year comes about. It might not be this season, but if
at the end of twelve months, certainly that will have caused death.
What if you're in a place like, you know, LA where it's
all the same season all the year? I don't know. There's also
an interesting debate in the פוסקים poskim because we rule the הלכה
halacha of י"ב חודש yud beis chodesh about if it's an עיבור
ibur year do we have thirteen months? I'm going to ask...
yeah, right. But if it's about seasons, presumably you shouldn't, and the
גמרא Gemara consistently says twelve months, right, it doesn't say שנה shanah
or something. You had a question, Michael?
Well, you know, he also doesn't
answer the challenge on רב.
Rav. We're having an answer.
Yeah, no, but also רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
doesn't, you don't answer what happens if it stays the same, you
know, the other side.
That's true, presum... that's a good question. I don't know, maybe you
have to check otherwise.
That's a good question. And new and also, and I guess I
was trying to think about yesterday, because when we had ההוא דשביק
קרקשא, hahu dashvik karkasha, where the wings grew better and all that...
Yeah, but I guess that they mean to say that that really
wasn't a...
but it wouldn't have gotten better. Right, that's exactly the... the same
injury would not have gotten better. Other things could have. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Achah bar Yaakov, הלכה, halacha,
טרפה יולדת ומשבחת, treifah yoledes u'meshabbachas, that a טרפה treifah could give
birth and could get better in other areas. So if we see
an animal's health improving and you see an animal giving birth, it
is not evidence that it is not a טרפה, treifah, okay, because
it could be that it's dying in other ways that cannot be
detected.
אמר מימר, Amar Meimar, so now מימר Meimar said, so that's his
position that a טרפה treifah can give birth. Now by the way,
I should say, I want to say something about what the context,
halachic context of this discussion is. Okay, number one, it does not
mean if an animal's health is getting better or an animal can
give birth, it's a טרפה, treifah, if you have no evidence that
it's a טרפה. treifah. Those things could be based on other cause.
It also does not mean what you might be inclined to say,
which is, if an animal has an injury that we would clearly
declare it as a טרפה, treifah, it's got a hole in the
lung or whatever it has, and however it lives for twelve months
or its health gets better or it gives birth, we'll say, oh,
so this animal isn't a טרפה. treifah. No. You know, that actually
is what the ראשונים rishonim were challenged with, which is, if טרפות
treifos are supposed to die, how come sometimes we have evidence that
it doesn't? But nobody said, oh, well that will mean that this
animal is a...
Right, stupid animal, exactly. That's what they'll say, something like that. מעשה
נסים, Ma'aseh nissim, but this animal is, that doesn't change the הלכה.
halacha. Okay, now there is one opinion out there, the מהרש"ל, Maharshal,
that does say that like ninety-nine percent of animals with טרפות treifos
will die, but there is like, you know, one percent of animals
that have these injuries that... Outliers. Right, whatever, right, that don't die.
So that's a way to make it that it doesn't contradict our
principle that a טרפה treifah will die. Okay, there's
always... The animal was still a טרפה. treifa. The only relevance of
these tests whether it lives or not is if there was something
occurred like it got clawed at, it was a דרוסה drusa case,
it got something you don't know if it had a hole in
the membrane or not a hole in the membrane and you don't
know and then you could say well given that it survived or
given that it was able to give birth now we can use
evidence that it's not a טרפה. treifa. An interesting issue that comes
up in the פוסקים poskim is let's say it's not a case
about a particular animal in front of you. Let's say there's a
מחלוקת הפוסקים machlokes haposkim whether a certain thing makes it a טרפה,
treifa, like you know does this type of a hole make it
a טרפה, treifa, you know these ראשונים rishonim say yes and those
ראשונים rishonim say no whatever the case might be. Can you then
say well given that we see animals that have this injury and
they don't die within a year clearly the הלכה halacha is like
those פוסקים poskim that say that it's not a טרפה. treifa. Okay
so that's interesting right? It's not just saying that we don't know
the physical realities here we're saying well using this to determine which
of the פוסקים poskim are correct and there interestingly the basic ruling
is that we can use that evidence to rule in favor of
certain פוסקים poskim against other פוסקים. poskim. What we can't do is
say that if something that we have established clearly you know in
the גמרא Gemara by tradition is a טרפה treifa that that gets
changed based on the evidence. You know that's clear like the list
is fixed. But if we don't know about a particular animal or
we actually don't know about a הלכתי halachic ruling then we could
use the evidence based on does the animal survive or not survive
in twelve months. So that's the relevance the context of this discussion.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara has said we have a ruling
that a טרפה treifa can give birth and therefore presumably the way
you deal with if you have a doubt is not to see
whether it can give birth but to wait twelve months.
Right so he's still saying the twelve months. Well it doesn't say
how many רב
אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov he hasn't said the twelve
months. That seems to be the other thing we're going back to
but it hasn't been said by him. Right now all he said
is that a טרפה treifa can give birth. So
we've even totally basically yeah. אמר אמימר Amar Ameimar הני ביעי דטרפה.
hanei beiei d'treifa. Now let's say you have eggs
from a hen that's a טרפה. treifa. Now the principle is that
any food product that comes from an animal that's not kosher, even
if it is a kosher species but just happens to be not
kosher in this particular animal because it's a טרפה, treifa, that product
is also not kosher. So milk from a cow that's a טרפה
treifa is not kosher, eggs from a chicken that's a טרפה treifa
is not kosher. Is that animal or what? That's going to be
the question. Okay so now you have a hen now you have
a chicken that has that's a טרפה treifa that has eggs. So
let's take a look. שחלא קמא אסירא shachala kama asira the first
bundle is forbidden meaning it got attacked by some weasel or something
and it became a טרפה treifa but it was right but when
it was attacked it was still carrying eggs so that first thing
that it gave birth to that when it was carrying when it
became a טרפה treifa that's forbidden. מכאן ואילך הוי ליה זה וזה
גורם ומותר mikan v'eilach havi lei zeh v'zeh goreim u'mutar afterwards it
is double causes and permissible. What's a double cause? It is assuming
that these are fertilized eggs. We'll discuss non-fertilized eggs in a minute.
So if they're fertilized eggs so presumably you're interested in the chicks
you're not really interested in them as eggs. So anyway they're fertilized
eggs so what causes the chick to develop in the egg? It
is both the contribution of the mother and the father. So therefore
even though the mother is a טרפה treifa the father is not
a טרפה treifa and therefore if there are two causes it is
not totally a product of the mother this one causes and that
one causes and therefore you know you might have said as long
as there's one bad contributor that's enough but that's a whole debate
זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh goreim and here we say as long
as the mother's not the only contributor the animal is actually okay.
So that's why the eggs afterwards are the chicks afterwards are okay.
But the one it was already impregnated with when it became a
טרפה treifa those were considered part of the mother and the status
of טרפה treifa that applied to the mother applied to the eggs
it was currently carrying. But the eggs that came later are not
just a part of the mother they are seen as being created
by the mother and also the sperm of the father and therefore
they are permissible. Yes Charlie.
But the mother contributes just as much as the father and is
still טרפה treifa even later on.
The mother what?
If the mother's ova and the
father's sperm yes and the mother remains a טרפה treifa right.
Right but the mother is still producing טרפה treifa ova then that...
Yes but her טרפה treifa ova when they are fertilized eggs and
we're interested in the chicks not in the eggs right? So when
they're fertilized eggs what creates the chick is the contribution of the
mother and the father. So you have a טרף treif contributor and
a non-טרף treif contributor and therefore it is it's not like you
mixed טרף treif ingredient with a non-טרף treif ingredient right? This is
something completely new but it was caused by a טרפה treifa origin
and a non-טרפה treifa origin and this position is זה וזה גורם
zeh v'zeh goreim is מותר mutar that's okay.
I would think it would be the other way around because the
hen created an ovum and it was fertilized while the hen was
still טרפה treifa and then it got clawed for instance. Yes and
now it's טרפה treifa so that egg ought to be fine and
then future eggs would be bad. I would think it would be
the other way around.
Oh because... Oh, because this originally began its life, okay, right, I
understand that. You could have said that. The גמרא Gemara says no,
based on sort of the principle of like עובר ירך אמו, Ubar
yerech imo, that this is like a part of the mother, so
the same way that a שחיטה shechita of the mother works for
the for the fetus, a טרפה treifa of the mother applies to
the fetus as well. But what came afterwards, right? Well why don't
you say עובר ירך אמו Ubar yerech imo for what came afterwards?
Because the assumption is that well what came afterwards is sort of
viewed in the context of the developed chick and the, you know,
contributions of the father as well. But you're right, it's a little
bit it's a little fuzzy. You know, you could have gone the
other way, yeah.
So clearly אמימר Amemar is going on the position of רב אחא
בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov that it's זה וזה גורם.
Zeh Vezeh Gorem. Well, that's what we're going to exactly say. Okay.
So אתי רב אשי לאמימר, Aisi Rav Ashi l'Amemar, so Rav Ashi
asked Amemar, ושוין דביצת טרפה שאסורה משום דגדלה באיסור. Veshavin debeitzas treifa
she'asura mishum degadla be'isur.
So you have a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית
הלל Beis Hillel
about if an animal if a chicken is a נבילה, neveila, right,
it died, it got attacked and died, and it wasn't שחוטה, shechted,
and you opened it up and there was an egg inside of
it, a developed egg. The way it's described is כמותה נמכרת בשוק.
kemosa nimkeret bashuk. It's complete. It's as complete as you would imagine
to see in a marketplace. It really has the shell on and
everything. Is it considered part of the mother and it becomes a
נבילה neveila with the mother, or because it's completely finished there it's
already independent of the mother even though it was still in the
mother's womb? So so that's a debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel
and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, whether that's כשר kosher or טרף. treif.
But but they say they agree, that's when the animal died, that's
a נבילה, neveila, but they agree ושוין בביצת טרפה שאסורה, veshavin beveitzas
treifa she'asura,
that if the animal became a טרפה treifa and the egg was
not found in the animal but then came out of the mother—okay,
or you שחט shechted it maybe and you did find it in
the animal, but either way it became a טרפה—in treifa those cases
it's forbidden. Now why is it worse than the נבילה neveila case,
right? Why should the נבילה neveila be okay if it's a finished
egg and the טרפה treifa be no good? מפני שגדלה באיסור, mipnei
shegadla be'isur, because it grew when she was prohibited. Meaning what's that
case? The animal became a טרפה, treifa, you waited a day and
then you שחט shechted it. So the egg that grew within the
last day was growing in the womb of a טרפה treifa animal.
When the animal was a נבילה—when neveila it was a nice live
animal and attacked by a cat and died at the spot—right, the
egg did not continue to grow after the problem had existed. She
was dead. Okay. So so here though they agree that it's a
problem because it continued to grow in the in the chicken, in
the hen, after she became a טרפה. treifa.
Alright, so—but
sorry, but before she was dead.
There are two scenarios. One is one is a hen was killed
by a cat and is a נבילה neveila now and is dead.
You cut it open, you find an egg. So there there's a
debate, is that egg כשר kosher or טרף? treif? Maybe it's considered
independent of the mother. Okay. There's another case, a case two, the
hen was attacked by a cat and she just became a טרפה.
treifa. And then she survived another few days and then you שחט
shechted her a week later and then you find the egg. So
there they say oh that egg is definitely forbidden because in the
last week it's been growing in the womb of this טרפה. treifa.
Okay, well if you שחט shechted it right away,
presumably there's still a minute, you know, that it was growing presumably,
okay? As opposed to here the exact problem exists as to, you
know, it was momentary. Okay. So so the גמרא Gemara says anyway
מפני שגדלה באיסור. mipnei shegadla be'isur. So
so there you see you don't say זה וזה גורם, zeh vezeh
gorem, right? So how is that different? I'm sorry, there you say
that it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says התם דספנה מארעא. hasam
desafna me'ara.
That is talking about an unfertilized egg. The way the גמרא Gemara
uses it is that she is becoming fertilized by the ground or
she is getting warmed by the ground. Version of, right. Well, it's
an unfertilized egg, so it's not a זה וזה גורם. zeh vezeh
gorem. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says well
wait which which—the case
where the egg is a—where בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי
Beis Shammai agree that the egg is a טרפה. treifa. Why don't
you say it's זה וזה גורם? zeh vezeh gorem? So the גמרא
Gemara says oh because it's unfertilized. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, 'cause actually it's a little confusing 'cause the way I described
it to you it was only the amount that the egg continued
to grow after she became a טרפה, treifa, which there was no
father contributing anyway. So the גמרא Gemara actually imagines the case—I actually
jumped to the second suggestion that the גמרא—that Gemara the hen became
a טרפה treifa and then she became fertilized with an egg. And
even okay and that even there we're saying that the egg is
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says why is it a problem?
What about the father? What about זה וזה גורם? zeh vezeh gorem?
So it says no, it's an unfertilized egg. So the גמרא Gemara
says that's
that's her euphemism for unfertilized?
Yeah, she's getting it from the ground.
לישני בשכחא קמא. lishni beshichcha kama. Why not—this is the way I
described the case—why not talk about what she was carrying when she
became a טרפה? treifa? That would then be consistent because we said
just a minute ago that what she's carrying when she became a
טרפה treifa does apply. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אי כן
גדלה, in ken gadla, would not have said that the egg grew
when she was אסורה, asura, it would have said גמרה מבעי ליה,
gamra mibai leh, it finished growing when she was אסורה. asura. So
the fact that it says that they agree in that case because
it grew when she was אסורה asura means even a newly fertilized
egg. So what have we said? We have said now, yes implicitly,
this is the reason we're bringing it down, that Michael can anticipate,
that these hens that
are
anything she's carrying when she became a טריפה treifa applies to what's
in her body as well. If,
however, it's something new, then it's זה וזה גורם zeh v’zeh gorem
and it's not a problem. How about this case about בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai where they say that a
hen that’s a טריפה, treifa, the eggs are a problem? So that
would either be again something that she was already carrying, but the
language doesn't sound that way, so then it would be a case
where it's an unfertilized egg. Okay, very good. Now we're going to
get back to our question. Okay, wait, one minute, we're not done
yet. Okay, so אלא הא דתנן, ella ha d’tnan, that which we
taught, or הא דתניא, ha d’tanya, that which we taught in a
ברייתא: braisa: ולד טריפה, vlad treifa, if you have an animal, a
cow, or whatever, a sheep, that was born from a mother who’s
a טריפה; treifa; רבי אליעזר אומר לא יקרב לגבי מזבח, Rabbi Eliezer
omer lo yikarev legabei mizbe'ach, do not bring it on the מזבח,
mizbeiach, ורבי יהושע v’Rabbi Yehoshua אומר, omer excuse me, יקרב, yikarev, you
can bring it on the מזבח. mizbeiach. Okay, so that’s a question.
Is it a טריפה treifa or not? The child of a טריפה
treifa can be brought as a קרבן, korban, which, you know, is
even—I mean, we would first ask if it can be eaten by
people, but okay. So במאי קמיפלגי? b’mai kamifligi? What’s that debate about?
בשנטרפה ולבסוף עיברה, b’shenitrefa u’levasof ibra, it has to be that first
it became a טריפה, treifa, right? And then it became pregnant. And
then it's this question of זה וזה גורם. zeh v’zeh gorem. The
mother contributes and the father contributes after the mother’s already a טריפה.
treifa. Okay, then the mother became pregnant. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer סבר
savar זה וזה גורם אסור, zeh v’zeh gorem assur, if this one
causes and that one causes, so one negative cause of this child,
therefore it's forbidden. You could make this a whole wonderful metaphor about
positive and negative influences. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua סבר savar זה וזה
גורם מותר, zeh v’zeh gorem mutar, that if this one causes and
that one causes it's permissible. Okay, so exactly this issue about the
animal is forbidden, the mother is forbidden, but now she becomes newly
pregnant with the seed of the father. Is that going to be
whether it's an egg or whether it's going to be a child,
is that going to be a product of a טריפה treifa or
not? This is now debated in the context of the child of
a cow or of a sheep used for a קרבן korban when
the mother became pregnant after she was a טריפה. treifa. All right,
so we said before that it was not a problem; here we're
seeing that it is debated. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי,
ei hachi, if that's true, עד דמפלגי לגבוה לפלגו להדיוט? ad d’mifligi
l’gavoa liflego l’hedyot?
Why are you just arguing whether it can be used as a
קרבן? korban? Say that you—you know, those that say it's forbidden, you
can't even—even a normal person can't eat it.
So להודיעך כוחו l’hodi’acha kocho so הדיוט hedyot is a more of
a חידוש? chiddush?
Well, to say it's אסור, assur, meaning not only is it אסור
assur for a קרבן, korban, it's even אסור assur for a layperson.
Okay, right, because if you just say it's אסור assur for a
קרבן, korban, you might say, well, it's tainted, in principle it's not
really forbidden, it's not really the product of a טריפה, treifa, meaning
you could imagine a position that says זה וזה גורם zeh v’zeh
gorem is a big enough problem not to use as a קרבן,
korban, but not a big enough problem that you as a layperson
can't eat it. But the גמרא Gemara is framing it like it's
all or nothing. So if it's really all or nothing, why not
even say that a layperson can't eat it? לפלגו להדיוט? liflego l’hedyot?
להודיעך כוחו דרבי יהושע, l’hodi’acha kocho d’Rabbi Yehoshua,
to tell you the חידוש chiddush of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that
says it's permissible, דאפילו לגבוה נמי שרי, d’afilu l’gavoa nami sharei, that
it's even permissible as a קרבן, korban, it's so permissible. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולפלוג להדיוט להודיעך כוחו דרבי אליעזר, u’liflog l’hedyot l’hodi’acha
kocho d’Rabbi Eliezer, why not tell me about a layperson eating it,
to tell me the strength of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that even
a layperson cannot eat it, and it's not only אסור assur as
a קרבן, korban, it's even אסור assur for a layperson? דאפילו להדיוט
נמי אסור, d’afilu l’hedyot nami assur,
it's even forbidden for a layperson. The גמרא Gemara says no, כוח
דהיתרא עדיף ליה. koach d’heiteira adif lei.
It's a bigger חידוש chiddush to tell you how far you'll go
to say something is permitted. It's always easier to say that something
is forbidden. As רש״י Rashi says, it doesn't require any broad shoulders
to say something is forbidden, it's always the play-it-safe approach, but it
takes really broad shoulders to say it's permitted. So we want to
say the one who says it's permitted, completely permitted even for a
קרבן. korban. But again, you could imagine a middle position where don't
use it as a קרבן korban but you're allowed to eat it,
but that the גמרא Gemara is not taking—it's all or nothing. So
now we have said a טריפה treifa can give birth and can
become pregnant—whatever, we’re assuming all of that. What happens by something that
is an offspring of a טריפה treifa and a father? Not milk,
not unfertilized eggs, which are completely a problem, but something that’s a
byproduct of father and mother. That's a question of זה וזה גורם.
zeh v’zeh gorem. There are those that say it's completely permitted, there
are those that say it's completely forbidden.
Okay, now, ומודי בביצת טריפה דאסורה, u’modi b’beitzas treifa d’assura, and this
idea that they agreed by the... wait
a minute... and so even though there's this debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua by the child of a
טריפה, treifa, this case of the קרבן, korban, they agree that a
normal egg of a טריפה treifa is forbidden. Why? בדספנא מארעא, bid’safna
me’ara, because that’s a case of an unfertilized egg. דחד גורם הוא,
d’chad gorem hu, that it’s only one cause. Okay, so they debate—רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua debate the issue of
the actual child of a טריפה treifa which is זה וזה גורם.
zeh v’zeh gorem. They don't debate the milk or the eggs; that's
only one cause and that is forbidden. Now, that all assumes that
a טריפה treifa can give birth, and that's, remember, how we introduced
this, right? We said אמר רב אחא בר יעקב הלכה טריפה יולדת—a
Amar Rav Achai bar Yaakov, halacha treifa yoledes טריפה treifa can give
birth. So we’re able to have this whole discussion. But now we're
going to see what happens if you say a טרפה treifah can't
give birth, obviously we'll have to reframe the whole discussion. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
רב אחא סבר לה כרב
אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha savar lah ke'Rav Acha bar Yaakov ומתני
לה לדאמימר כדאמרינן. u'masni lah l'damemar k'damrinan. So רב אחא Rav Acha
held like רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov that said
a טרפה treifah can give birth, and told over אמימר's Amemar position
like we just articulated it. This whole discussion about did it have,
you know, is the eggs coming after בהמה טרפה behemah treifah or
from before it was a טרפה? treifah? Because you could imagine eggs
after it was a טרפה. treifah. That's how we've said it so
far.
The words of רב אחא? Rav Acha? I know the רב אחא...
Rav Acha...
the רב אחא Rav Acha we haven't mentioned. He was just the
one that apparently told this whole thing over. Okay, or he, or
we're also saying he also told it over the way we just
had it above. Okay, however, רבינא לא סבר לה כרב אחא בר
יעקב. Ravina lo savar lah k'Rav Acha bar Yaakov. רבינא Ravina did
not hold of רב אחא בר יעקב. Rav Acha bar Yaakov. He
holds that a טרפה treifah cannot give birth. Okay, and
therefore ומתני ליה לדאמימר בהאי לישנא. u'masni lei l'damemar be'hai lishna. He
had a completely different version of what אמימר Amemar said. Yes, אמימר
Amemar was talking about the hen and the טרפה treifah and this
and that, but it would have to have been a completely different
version if you believe that a טרפה treifah could not give birth.
So what was his version of
אמימר? Amemar? ומתני לה בהאי לישנא. u'masni lah be'hai lishna. אמר אמימר
הני בי דספק טרפה, Amar Amemar hanei bei d'safek treifah, eggs of
a doubtful טרפה. treifah. The keyword we'd add now is doubtful, ספק.
safek. Since we're saying a טרפה treifah cannot give birth, we're going
to use the issue of is it having eggs or not to
determine whether it was a טרפה treifah or not. And here's where
the relevance of is it of the twelve months or the test
plays out in cases of doubtful טרפה. treifah. Okay, so הני בי
דספק טרפה, hanei bei d'safek treifah, eggs of a chicken that is
a doubtful טרפה, treifah, דשכלא קמא, d'shichla kama, if they are ones
that it was carrying in the first... what do you call it,
not bundle, what do you call that when you have a cluster?
A cluster, something of eggs. Anyway, in the first
cluster, but hens only give birth one egg at a time, right?
Yeah. Okay, so maybe it's not a cluster. Anyway, anyway, the first,
anyway, the first, anyway, that were in there originally... I'm not sure
the exact translation of שכלא. shichla. רש"י Rashi says פושטא. pushta. Okay,
I don't know, anyway.
He's suggesting here in the context that it's a cluster and they
detach one at a time.
Aha, that's interesting.
Like at various sizes, I guess they're growing in...
Oh, that's interesting. Oh, okay, okay, that's interesting. So cluster does work.
He's...
do some birds give birth to like multiple eggs?
Yeah, but hens only have more than one.
Yeah, in one way.
So David is saying they could have a cluster and it was
carrying a whole cluster when it became a טרפה, treifah, but it's
only depositing them at various stages.
Modern hens are producing eggs almost on a constant.
Right, so they have to have some of them developing in their
body as they are continuing. Okay, fine. So, if you have an
animal that's a doubtful טרפה, treifah, דשכלא קמא, d'shichla kama, if it
became a doubtful טרפה, treifah, it was clawed at or whatever, you
know, while it was carrying the current cluster, so then, are these
eggs kosher or not? So here's how you can figure it out,
because you can't figure out from the fact that it was having
these eggs because they were carrying it before it became a טרפה.
treifah. But here's how you'll figure it out: משינן להו. Mashinan lehu.
You put the eggs aside and you wait with them. אי הדרא
ותנא, Ei hadra v'tana, if the chicken gets another cluster of eggs,
she becomes laden, literally, so she gets another cluster after this injury
occurred, okay then, אי הדרא ותנא שרינן, ei hadra v'tana sharainan, then
we permit the first cluster because now we say oh, she now
has become pregnant again or whatever, has had more eggs, so we
know that she's not a טרפה. treifah. ואי לא אסירן, V'ei lo
asiran, if she never has more eggs, we make them forbidden. So
now we're using the question of does she have further eggs, not
as זה וזה גורם, zeh vezeh gorem, but to determine whether she
had become a טרפה treifah or not.
So דשכלא קמא d'shichla kama is not necessarily even אסור. asur.
Right, if she then becomes... because it was only a doubtful טרפה,
treifah, and the fact that she's having more eggs shows us she
was not a טרפה. treifah. Okay, so a very different teaching of
אמימר Amemar about using it to determine was the chicken a טרפה
treifah or not. So איתיבי רב אשי לאמימר. eisivi Rav Ashi l'Amemar.
So רב אשי Rav Ashi asked אמימר, Amemar, ומודין בביצת טרפה שאסורה.
u'modin b'veitzas treifah she'asurah. We had that statement about בית הלל בית
שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai that they agree that the egg of
a טרפה treifah is forbidden, מפני שגדלה באיסור, mipnei she'gidlah b'issur, because
it grows in the mother when the mother is already forbidden. So
how can it grow in the mother if the mother is a
טרפה? treifah? That's clearly a ודאי vadai טרפה, treifah, not a ספק
safek טרפה, treifah, and we're saying it's forbidden. How could that happen
if טרפות treifahs don't give birth? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back to him, התם בשכלא קמא. hasam b'shichla kama. No, that's
talking not about new eggs, new eggs it won't have if it's
a טרפה. treifah. That's talking about eggs that it was currently carrying
when it became a טרפה. treifah. So the גמרא Gemara says בשכלא...
b'shichla... where are we... אם כן גדלה? im kein gidlah? The teacher
said they grew when she was already אסורה, asurah, which sounds like
from the very beginning. גמרה מיבעי ליה, Gamra mibayei lei, it should
have said they completed when she was already a טרפה. treifah. So
it says fine, תני גמרה, tani gamra, so have it say גמרה
gamra or it means גמרה. gamra. That's not going to bother me.
So this discussion of בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai
about eggs that grew in a chicken that's a
טרפה treifah is not new eggs, that wouldn't happen according to him,
it's eggs that were already in the chicken when she became a
טרפה treifah and continued to develop. Okay, אלא הא דתנן, ela ha
d'tnan, now this debate of רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer And Rabbi Yehoshua,
this is going to be a challenge, right? Because they're talking about
a child that's born from a mother that's a טרפה. treifa. אלא
הא דתנן, Ella ha detnan, ולד טרפה, vlad treifa, the child of
a טרפה, treifa, can you use it for a קרבן? korban? רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer... אומר omer, לא יקרב לגבי מזבח, lo yikarev l’gabei
mizbeiach, don't bring it on the altar. רבי יהושע אומר יקרב, Rabbi
Yehoshua omer yikarev, you could bring it on the altar. במאי קמיפלגי,
B'mai kamiflegi, what would the case be? כשעיברה ולסוף נטרפה. K'she'ibra u-l'sof
nitrefa. You'll have to say the case is, is that it can't
be she first became a טרפה treifa and then got pregnant, because
according to you that would never happen. So what must the case
be? So the case must
be that she became pregnant and then she became a טרפה. treifa.
Okay, but then what are they debating? What's the question about what
the status of the child is? It can't be זה וזה גורם,
zeh va-zeh gorem, the father's already out of the picture, right? The
mother first became pregnant, the father's out of the picture, and then
she became a טרפה. treifa. So there you cannot talk about the
father and the mother joint contributors, etc., because there it's just the
mother carrying her fetus and now she became a טרפה. treifa. So
what would the debate be about the status of the child? So
what?
No, that's easy then, if you say...
Okay, so let's take a... Yeah. במאי קמיפלגי, B'mai kamiflegi, what's the
debate about? We had that whole thing, you know, if you say
עובר ירך אמו. ubar yerech imo. There you go. Exactly. במאי קמיפלגי,
B'mai kamiflegi, כשעיברה ולסוף נטרפה, k'she'ibra u-l'sof nitrefa, so she's already pregnant,
then she became a טרפה. treifa. So it's not about the father,
he's out of the picture when she becomes a טרפה. treifa. And
רבי אליעזר סבר עובר ירך אמו הוא. Rabbi Eliezer savar ubar yerech
imo hu. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds the fetus is like a
part of the mother, and therefore if the mother became a טרפה,
treifa, the fetus became a טרפה. treifa. And רבי יהושע סבר עובר
לאו ירך אמו הוא. Rabbi Yehoshua savar ubar lav yerech imo hu.
The fetus is not part of the mother. The mother could become
a טרפה treifa but not the fetus. So it has nothing to
do with the father, he's out of the picture. The moment... the
mother will not become pregnant after she became a טרפה. treifa. It's
just the mother and her fetus, she becomes a טרפה, treifa, does
that apply to the fetus or not? I do want to point
out, by the way, without getting into the details, תוספות Tosafot points
out that this is... does not exactly parallel the debate before about
the egg. By the egg, it would sort of, you know, it
was more likely... it was more sort of taken for granted that
the status of a hen applied to the egg, whereas here it's
debated whether the status of the mother applies to the fetus. And
תוספות Tosafot says there's an obvious difference, right, that the fetus is...
has its own life force in it. And it also... the egg
is also more just intertwined in the inside of the hen, physically,
and also it doesn't have its own life force. So you... it's
more obvious you say the egg is part of the mother than
you say that the fetus is part of the mother, and that's
why this is debated. Yes.
I would have thought it the other way around because the, at
least in a placental mammal, the fetus is connected to the mother
through the placenta. Right. Whereas an egg is completely shelled off from
the mother hen.
When the egg... when the shell finally develops. So the question is
at what stage. Like, before the shell has developed, I mean, it's...
it's really very soft, isn't it? You know, the shell comes at
the very, very end, the hard shell, from what I understand. I
mean, based on גמרא. Gemara.
But anyway...
but reptile and mammal eggs are soft. They're more leathery than shell.
But I think the hard egg comes at the end. Anyway, תוספות
Tosafot works with those distinctions, okay? And we will see, as we
talked about yesterday, that even if you say עובר ירך אמו, ubar
yerech imo, that does not mean completely the part of the mother,
there does have some independence. Okay, but that's what it debates. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So what are they arguing
about? רבי אליעזר סבר עובר ירך אמו. Rabbi Eliezer savar ubar yerech
imo. It's part of the mother. So if the mother's a טרפה,
treifa, the fetus is טרפה. treifa. רבי יהושע סבר עובר לאו ירך
אמו הוא. Rabbi Yehoshua savar ubar lav yerech imo hu. It's not
part of the mother. So the גמרא Gemara says once again. אי
הכי נמי ליפלגו בגבוה ליפלגו להדיוט. Ee hachi nami nifligu b'gavoah nifligu
l'hedyot. Why are they only debating about a קרבן? korban? If it's
not a problem, it shouldn't be a problem at all. להודיעך כוחו
דרבי יהושע, L'hodi'acha kocho d'Rabbi Yehoshua, to tell you the strength of
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, that it's... that it's not a problem even
for the... for a קרבן. korban. וליפלוג להדיוט להודיעך כוחו דרבי אליעזר.
V'niflog b'hedyot l'hodi'acha kocho d'Rabbi Eliezer. Talk about a layperson to tell
you the strength of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that it's... it's a
real טרפה treifa and even a layperson can't eat it according to
him. כוח דהתירא עדיף ליה. Koach d'heteira adif lei. They'd rather tell
you the strength of the one who permits it, that he permits
it even for a קרבן. korban. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ומודים ודאי בביצת טרפה שאסורה. U-modim vaday b'veitzat treifa she-asura. Why do
they, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, agree... or
בית הלל בית שמאי, Beit Hillel Beit Shammai, but whatever, agree... that
that a ביצה beitza of a טרפה treifa is forbidden? So what's
the case? It can't be an animal had the egg after the
chicken after she became a טרפה. treifa. We're now saying that doesn't
happen. So that is בדשחלה קמא. bi-deshachla kama. What she's carrying before
she became a טרפה. treifa. Now she's carrying it before she became
a טרפה treifa and then she became a טרפה. treifa. So okay,
we understand that it's not about the father and that it could
happen because she was already carrying it. But why isn't it the
same debate about עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo or עובר לאו
ירך אמו? ubar lav yerech imo? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? גופא היא, Gufa hi, it's all
part of her body. That actually, yeah, a minute ago I said
it was תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot discusses some of the more details,
but here actually it's basically the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara saying
that even though they debated whether עובר ubar was ירך אמו, yerech
imo, they all agreed that the egg is ירך אמו. yerech imo.
Okay, the egg does not have its own life, and here they
really do agree that the egg is ירך אמו. yerech imo. Okay,
so just to review what we said. We have said that there's
those that say that a animal that's a טרפה treifa can have
birth after she became a טרפה. treifa. That's true, we can talk
about what happens if an animal that's a טריפה treifa becomes impregnated
by a rooster or by a male cow or sheep or whatever,
not cow, a bull, whatever, is the offspring, it's a זה וזה
גורם, zeh ve-zeh gorem, is the offspring permissible or forbidden? That's one
area of focusing on this debate. The other approach is to say
but if it's milk or eggs that are unfertilized then clearly it's
forbidden and that's where everybody agrees, that's the מודה. modeh. Then there's
another approach which is saying that no, a טריפה treifa cannot give
birth. So the question after an animal became a טריפה, treifa, does
she have eggs, an offspring, whatever, that would determine whether she, if
it was doubtful, if it was a ספק, safek, that would determine
whether she was a טריפה treifa and therefore it would allow us
to eat the eggs that she gave birth to earlier that were
under doubt. That's the other approach. What type of debate does exist?
The debate exists if she became a טריפה treifa when carrying the
eggs, carrying the fetus, are those part of the mother or not?
By the fetus it's debated whether עובר ירך אמו, ubar yerech imo,
but by the eggs it's agreed that the eggs are considered much
more of a part of the mother than the fetus. Okay, because
the fetus really has its own life in a way that the
egg does not, so by the egg everybody does agree. Okay. Yes.
כוח דהיתירא עדיף koach de-heteira
adif means here that he'd rather tell you this side than the
other side.
The תנא Tanna would rather tell you right this side.
But yes, but the reason is, hopefully there's another means, there's another
use.
Well, I think they're intertwined, meaning the normal usage of כוח דהיתירא
עדיף koach de-heteira adif means is that it takes greater sort of
strength in your position, broader shoulders and greater confidence in your position
to say something is permitted than to say it's forbidden. But I
think that's why the תנא Tanna would rather tell you it because
he's telling you the one who says it's permitted is willing to
go so far to say it's permitted even in the case of
a
קרבן. korban. Now why would he rather tell you that than tell
you the one who says it's forbidden is willing to go so
far to say it's forbidden even for lay person? Because it's a
bigger, it's more of a statement to go far with a היתר
heter than to go far with an איסור. issur. I mean I
think they're logically connected, right?
I was just wondering if the גמרא Gemara also uses it in
that other way or if that's later.
To say explicitly that it requires greater strength to take up this
position?
No, no, I'm just wondering if the phrase כוח דהיתירא עדיף koach
de-heteira adif appears in the גמרא Gemara in the sense
of one should rather or
we prefer a lenient ruling to a stricter ruling. I don't think
the גמרא Gemara says that. I don't know, has it is it
used that way?
You've heard it used that way? I mean there, you know, when
you discuss those questions in a way we had that articulated before,
the tension between עד מתי אתה מכלה ממונם של ישראל ad matay
ata machal mamonam shel Yisrael versus עד מתי אתה מאכיל לישראל טריפות,
ad matay ata ma-achil l-Yisrael treifos, you know? So how much are
you trying to protect against transgression, how much are you trying to
protect against undue, you know, compromising, you know, a people's freedom or
liberty, you know, whatever, just life. But I don't think כוח דהיתירא
עדיף, koach de-heteira adif, I don't think, maybe informally it's used to
say what you said but I don't think that's ever a meaning
that the גמרא Gemara gives it. Yes.
I'm not sure I understand. Are you saying that a fetus can
exist independently whereas an egg...
No, no, no, no. But that a fetus does have its growing
inside of the mother, you can, you know, and you see it
has its own life, you know, force even while it's in the
mother whereas an egg doesn't have any life force in the mother.
Because when after it's laid, you know, it might start the, you
know, the chick will start develop when does the chick start developing?
After it's laid, right? I don't know if that's true.
I don't know if that's true immediately after it's fertilized but it's
not going to get very far...
but it doesn't get too far until it's laid. So it's not
considered to be a life yet inside of the mother, just considered
a part of the mother, eggs constantly.
What? Eggs for days, right, every day. It doesn't need to be
fertilized from some, if they're,
right, non-fertilized eggs.
Correct. That wouldn't be an issue at all. Yeah, exactly. Okay, exactly.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והלכתא, ve-hilchesa, the הלכה
halacha is, בזכר כל שנים עשר חודש. bezachar kol shneim asar chodesh.
By a male where you cannot do a test whether it can
have give birth or not, so the wait a minute, Michael,
I'll talk in a minute.
Okay. So then you use by 12 months. If it can if
there's a doubt and it lives for 12 months you know it's
not a טריפה. treifa. בנקבה benekeva by a
female כל שאינה יולדת. kol she-eina yoledes. If she does not give
birth, actually this is im- give
me a second,
this is imprecisely articulated because it should have said כל שיולדת, kol
she-yoledes, right? By זכר zachar if it lasts 12 months and by
a female as if it does give birth. So it's a little
imprecisely articulated. But anyway, the thing is, you would assume it means
that that's sufficient if she gives birth but certainly if she lasts
for 12 months. But I actually did some research and people don't
say it explicitly until you get to the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
and the שך, Shach, a classic commentator, finally says, oh, certainly of
course if the female also lives 12 months that's okay, but we
mean that it would also suffice if she gave birth in less
than 12 months, that would also be sufficient evidence. I know we
would assume it, but it's funny the way the גמרא Gemara articulates
it it's not so clear. So we basically are פוסקנינג, paskening, it's
interesting... Now we פוסקין paskin this, we're פוסקין paskening that a טריפה
treifa cannot give birth and you can use the fact that a
female gives birth if there's a case of doubt, not a case
of definite, but a case of doubt as evidence that she is
not a טריפה. treifa. Now, what do I want to say? Ah,
so there is interesting debate in the פוסקים poskim two things. Number
one is if we say a טריפה treifa אינה יולדת, aina yoledes,
do we also say a טריפה treifa is אינו מוליד? aino molid?
That a male טריפה treifa cannot impregnate. That is not discussed in
the גמרא Gemara and that's debated in the פוסקים. poskim. The other
question we ask is when we say a טריפה treifa אינה יולדת,
aina yoledes, does it mean a טריפה treifa cannot become pregnant or
does it mean that a טריפה treifa cannot, just will not give
birth? The גמרא Gemara before we can go back and try to
analyze it more closely, the impression one got is that a טריפה
treifa won't even become pregnant, not just won't deliver to term. Okay,
but that is somewhat debated as well whether it's אינה מעוברת aina
meuberes or אינה יולדת. aina yoledes. Okay, but the clear position is
that she certainly won't give birth and we can use this as
evidence. Alright, so this is primarily used in cases where there was
doubt, primarily the issues of doubt were things like דרוסה drusa and
נפולה, nefula, you know, those types of cases where it was talking
about after the animal falls off the roof, checking all the organs
and then there was question because we don't know how to check
those organs etc. So therefore you use this question of will it
live for 12 months or will it give birth as a way
of determining, but as I mentioned, interestingly some פוסקים poskim say you
can also use this to determine a debates of פסק. psak. If
you actually have evidence that animals with a particular problem live for
12 months, you know the פסק psak therefore would be incorrect. Okay,
so that's with the issue about whether it can give birth or
not. So now yes question? Go, go, Charlie first.
Yeah, that's maybe that should solve this issue of milk cows that
allegedly have injuries because they generally can continue to give birth.
Oh, that's an interesting question. Do but do they? I thought that
once they get a cow milking, they don't try to get get
it pregnant again, right?
They generally don't try to get it pregnant again.
So fine, if in one case you got it pregnant or whatever,
then you would use that as evidence. But it doesn't work for
the other 99 cows out of the 100 that you're not getting
pregnant again, right? So now and again the other problem with that
is if you can prove that it definitely has the puncture in
the inner organ, then any of this evidence is no good. This
evidence only works if there's a question, a question whether it has
the puncture, whether that puncture is a problem or not. If there's
some doubt, then you can use it. Now, that's interesting though. Again,
I have to look into what the whole discussions are around these
injections and the ספק safek טריפה treifa issue. But you know if
you want to say well let's do a test. Let's take 20
cows that have this injection, get them pregnant and once we've proven
it, we'll prove that this is not a you know not a
problem. But that's assuming that there's a
ספק. safek. Right. Right. But that's assuming that there's a ספק safek
and that that's a ספק safek that's general about is this whole
type of a hole make it a טריפה. treifa. If it's in
this particular cow all you've done is proven that these particular cows
are not a problem. You haven't gotten out of the problem in
general.
Yeah I just want to make sure I understand the bottom line.
So with the female cow, either living 12 months or giving birth
is sufficient and whether getting pregnant is sufficient we don't know?
Right, that's debated in the פוסקים. poskim.
And as for the male, if it lives 12 months, what about
if it
impregnates?
That's also debated in the פוסקים. poskim.
And what do people do?
They don't rely on it because we don't know that it's a
good test. Okay, so now the now the גמרא, Gemara, I did
want while we're talking about ספק, safek, there's one point I did
want to mention which I had forgotten to mention before when we
dealt with this category of ספק דרוסה. safek drusa. You remember that
was a whole category as well about ספק safek about an animal
that was clawed and maybe had this poison injected into it and
so on. You know, we had a whole time obviously difficult time
understanding what is this poison and all but also the גמרא Gemara
was strict about cases about ספק דרוסה, safek drusa, yeah and you
had to check and see if things turned red or not red
etc. So the רמב"ם Rambam makes an interesting statement that I just
wanted to share with you. He says as a general rule we're
not concerned about ספק safek by טריפות, treifos, right, things have a
חזקה chazaka and I mean you saw גמרות Gemaras that even when
there's a hole you could assume if you had a reason to
assume it came from the butcher or whatever you had other it
came afterwards, you get out of it. So as a general rule
we're not concerned about ספק. safek. The רמב"ם Rambam said the one
case in primarily we are concerned about ספק safek is ספק דרוסה
safek drusa by being clawed where we then have to check various
things. Why? Because he said that is really sort of the that's
really the paradigm טריפה treifa in the תורה, Torah, right? It didn't
occur to me when we were learning it, we get so caught
up in the halachic definition but the classic טריפה treifa is one
animal's clawed another animal.
So the רמב"ם Rambam says that's why they were stricter about the
דרוסה drusa case. Alright, anyway, back to us. So אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, כל בריה שאין בו עצם, kol biryah she-ein bo
etzem, so now we're having other related statements but not exactly about
טריפות. treifos. Any creature that has no bones like worms or invertebrates
essentially, אינו מתקיים י"ב חודש, eino miskayeim yud-beis chodesh, cannot live for
12 months. Charlie's saying absolutely not true. Snakes live for a long
time.
Actually snakes are vertebrates.
Oh they're vertebrates.
Sorry, but periodical cicadas will live for 17 years and they're invertebrates.
Wow.
Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
so what's the relevance of this להלכה? lehalacha? אמר רב פפא שמע
מינה מדרב הונא, Amar Rav Pappa shma mina mi-deRav Huna,
we can learn from Rav Huna, האי דאמר שמואל, hai de'amar Shmuel,
what Shmuel said, קישות שהתליעה באביה, kishus she'hisli'ah be'avi'ah, if a gourd
got wormy while it was sort of still growing. Now there is
a principle that the Torah says something is only forbidden, a bug,
if it's שרץ השרץ על הארץ, sheretz hashoretz al ha'aretz, if it
crawled on the ground, which means that if something, bugs developed in
a fruit or vegetable after it was picked, but they never were
on the ground—now it might be חזל Chazal thought that to have
happened by spontaneous generation, but it could still happen by the mother
depositing eggs inside the apple and then the insects are grown in
the apple and they've never walked on the ground—so that actually then
it is permissible. It is only, however, if the, interestingly, if the
apple was growing and this happened, it's forbidden because then they're moving
in the egg, but in the fruit or the gourd, but that
is connected to the ground, so it's like they're moving on the
ground.
Wait, so when is it permitted? If it's in a basket of
apples or something?
Yes, if it grew after, according to, if it grew after it
was picked. Okay, that's this statement. Okay, there's different parameters. Well, that's
what we're going to try to determine. But if it grew after
it was picked, then it was moving in an apple, but it
was never moving on the ground. But it was moving in the
apple or in the gourd when it was connected to the tree,
then that's all considered connected to the ground. That's Shmuel's statement.
Okay, and if you put it on the
ground?
Doesn't matter, it's not connected.
It was in the apple and the tree, you pick it, now
it's in the basket.
Yes. So if it's since the worm was there when it was
on the tree, according to Shmuel that's a problem.
How do you know that?
This is, that's what we're going to discuss. Let's take a look.
This is according to Shmuel, okay? What exactly are the parameters of
שרץ על הארץ shoretz al ha'aretz is debated. This is Shmuel's position.
So let's take a look. קישות שהתליעה באביה, kishus she'hisli'ah be'avi'ah,
if the gourd got worms while it was growing, אסורה, asurah, it's
forbidden, because then it's like the worm grew, walked on the ground.
So here's how you know, because we know that invertebrates don't live
for a year. So therefore, הני תמרי דכדא, hani tamrei de-chada, if
you have dates in a bowl, לבתר תריסר ירחי שתא, le-basar treisar
yarchei shata, if they've been sitting around in the bowl for more
than a year, and then you go ahead and inside of them
you find live worms, so if the worms are alive and they've
been sitting around for more than a year, based on the previous
teaching, those worms must have developed after it was already picked. So
therefore, שרין, sharyin, it is permissible. So you can have dry dates?
Dry, okay.
All right. Go ahead. But that they get wormy.
Yeah, they get wormy.
Yeah. Ah. Now, of course, we might wonder, maybe the worms came
from elsewhere and found their way in. Yeah,
so maybe, yeah, so all of these are interesting questions. Anyway, that's
what's the relevance of this teaching. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so okay,
so אמר רב, Amar Rav, Rav said, לית בקא בר יומא, leit
baka bar yoma, so now in a related way, Rav said there's
a בקא, baka, which is a certain type of a fly,
doesn't live out a day. There's some, and that is true, right?
There are some insects that die the day that they're born, right?
Right. ולית דידבא בר שתא, v'leit didva bar shata, and there's no
type of דידבא, didva, which is another type of a fly or
of a flying insect, that can live for a year. So certain,
this type of insect doesn't live for more than a day, this
type doesn't live for more than a year. Okay, אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, so Rav Pappa said to
Abaye, והאמרי אינשי, v'ha'amrei inshi, one minute, don't people have this, isn't
there just like little nice little story that people tell people? I
mean, that story, what's it called, like a whatever, משל, mashal, tale
or whatever, they say this. שבע שני דאמרה בקתא לבקרא, sheva shani
de'amrah bakta l'bakra, for seven years the female בקא baka was arguing
with the male בקא. baka. The female fly was arguing with the
male fly. דאמרה ליה, de'amrah lei, and she said to him, חזיתיה
לבר מחוזא, chazisiei l'bar Mechuza, I saw this person from the city
of מחוזא. Mechuza. Apparently in מחוזא Mechuza they were very
well-to-do and they were very fat, okay? So I saw this man
who was a, this person of מחוזא, Mechuza, דסחא במיא, de-sacha be-maya,
he went and he bathed in the water. So you know, for
a fly, these are more like, I think, mosquitoes than flies. Okay,
they were interested in the people's blood. So here's a nice tasty
meal. This fat guy from מחוזא Mechuza went and he bathed in
the water, וסליק, v'salik,
and he got up of the water, ואיכריך בסדיני, v'iskerich be-sadinei, he
wrapped himself in sheets, ואותית עליה, v'osis alei, and you sat on
him, ומצית מיניה, v'masis minei, and you sucked his blood, ולא הודעת
לי, v'lo hodas li, and you didn't tell me. So the woman
fly was arguing, the wife fly was arguing, or mosquito, was arguing
with the male mosquito for seven years. How could you be doing
this and not telling me? So, okay, so seven years, שבע, sheva,
to the first fly. So you see, they live for seven years.
Now, I have no idea what that was used to be an
example of, about insensitive men or about complaining wives, I don't know,
but anyway, that was the tale that people told. Now, how long
do mosquitoes live, by the way?
They bite and they die.
Yeah, but depends when they bite. They don't necessarily live just, anyway,
I don't know if this is mosquitoes either. Anyway, not seven years.
Okay, אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, ולטעמיך,
u-l'ta'ameich, you're trying to bring me a proof from these like little
stories? People tell. So how about this, הא דאמרי אינשי Ha d'amri
inshi people say, שיתין מני פרזלא Shitin manei parzla 60 mane, like
you know, pounds or tons of iron, תלו ליה בביקא
דקורסא talu lei b'vika d'kursa this mosquito whatever can hold on its
nose or its stinger. Okay, that's also what people say. Literally, you
think it can hold 60 pounds or even if it means you
know, מי איכא איהו גופא כמה הוי? Mi ika ihu gufa kama
hvei? Can that really be? How much do you think the mosquito
itself weighs? אלא, Ela, so rather than just saying these whole things
are just stories and don't have any meaning, here we're going to
say אלא, Ela, what does it mean when they say 60 pounds?
בשני דידיה B'shani didei in their pounds. Okay, in mosquito pounds. So
it's like when you say an ant can lift 100 times its
weight, right? It doesn't mean 100 times the weight of a human,
100 times an ant's weight, an ant measure. Okay, so therefore,
הכא נמי hacha nami here too, when we say 70 years, בשני
דידיה b'shani didei in dog years, in mosquito years. Okay, so in
mosquito years it was 70 years, but literally it won't live for
more than a day. All right, that was a nice little digression.
תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Now we are going on and back to
טריפה treifa and another—this doesn't mention—but just
so you know these things really do
live more than a day. All right, fine. תנן התם. Tnan hatam.
בהמה בעלת ה' רגליים. Behema ba'alat hamesh raglayim. Now we're going to
introduce another important principle. A five-legged animal, או שאין לה אלא שלוש,
o she'ein la ela shalosh, only three, הרי זה מום, harei ze
mum, it's a מום. mum. Now that's a מום mum is whether
you can bring it as a קרבן. korban. So fine. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, לא שנו אלא שחיסר ויתר ביד, Lo shanu
ela shechisar v'yiter b'yad, that's only if it has an extra forearm
or missing a forearm. אבל חיסר ויתר ברגל, Aval chisar v'yiter b'regel,
an extra or missing hind leg, טריפה. treifa. Now we already know
that an animal with a dislocated hind leg is a טריפה. treifa.
So certainly a missing hind leg is a טריפה. treifa. But what
about an extra hind leg? Why is that a problem? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, טריפה
נמי הוי. treifa nami hvei. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
כל יתר כנטול דמי, Kol yiter k'natul dami, anything extra is like
it's missing. Okay, so if you have an extra leg, it's like
it's missing a leg. And therefore, a missing leg, a hind leg,
makes an animal a טריפה. treifa.
Just like you can't add or subtract "bal tosif".
Now this I should say became a major source of problem for
the ראשונים Rishonim because people had clear evidence that animals with extra
limbs could live and were not טריפות treifot and they had to
deal with trying to deal with that contrary evidence. Now the רשב"א
Rashba does suggest that maybe this is not like the other טריפות.
treifot. Maybe other טריפות treifot we say can't live. This is based
on a principle, extra is like it's missing, which means maybe it
can live, it's just another principle that extra counts as if it
were missing. But we're not actually claiming that it won't live. Okay,
that's actually a nice resolution, but for whatever reason the רשב"א Rashba
doesn't like that. So he has real problems with the contrary evidence.
Well what's the practical difference? You can't eat it. מום, Mum, animal
with a מום. mum.
Yes, you can. It's just can't be a קרבן, korban, of course
it's kosher. Right, a disfigured animal can be eaten, sure. It's not
טריפה, treifa, מום mum is only a קרבן korban idea.
Like a broken leg or something?
Yeah, as long as it's not a טריפה. treifa. Sure.
What does the רשב"א Rashba do then? So he basically says you
have to reject the evidence. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so let's take a look at a couple of applications
very quickly about this.
ההיא חיותא דהוו לה תרתי סיני דאבי. Hahi chayuta d'havu lah tartei
sani d'evi. There was a certain animal that had two of these
סיני דאבי. sani d'evi. If you remember that was the type of
a thing near the first stomach of a cow that a lot
of the waste went into. איתו לקמיה דרבינא, Aitu l'kammeih d'Ravina, they
brought it before Ravina, וטרפה v'tarfah he said it's a טריפה treifa
מדיה דרב הונא. mi-dei d'Rav Huna. Based on Rav Huna, because if
it was missing that it'd be a טריפה, treifa, so an extra
one is also a טריפה. treifa. ואי שפיכן להדדי, V'ei shaphichan l'hadadi,
however, if the liquids go between them, כשירה, kshera, then it's kosher
because then it's really like it's one if the liquids are transferring
between the two.
ההוא גופסא דהוה נפקא מבי כסי להובלילא. Hahu gufsa d'hava nafka mibei
kassi l'huvelila. There was a certain tube that went from—I'm
sorry a certain what?—tube.
Okay, that went from the בית הכוסות beit hakosot which is the
second or third stomach of a cow to the other stomach. The
second and third stomach were connected by a tube. סבר רב אשי
למיטרפה. Savar Rav Ashi l'mitrefah. Rav Ashi wanted to declare it a
טריפה. treifa. אמר ליה הונא מר בר חייא לרב אשי, Amar lei
Huna Mar bar Chiya l'Rav Ashi, כל הני חיווי בבראי הכי אית
להו. kol hanei chivei b'varai hachi it lehu.
That's common in our animals, so that's not a problem. You know,
it's also not clear what he wanted to say יתר כנטול yiter
k'natul because an extra tube, but it's not like you can say
a comparable tube was missing, right? It's just a random extra appendage.
So he said anyway, he said that's not a problem, that happens
a lot in animals.
ההוא גופסא דהוה מעברא מבי כסי לכרסא. Hahu gufsa d'hava ma'avra mibei
kassi l'karsa. Then there was a tube that connected the בית הכוסות
beit hakosot to the כרס, kares, which was the first of the
stomachs. Okay. סבר מר בר רב אשי לאכשורה. Savar Mar bar Rav
Ashi l'achshurei. Now he wanted to say it's kosher because when it
connected the second and third stomach we said it's kosher. Now it's
connecting the second and the first, we want to say it's kosher.
אמר ליה רב אושעיא, Amar lei Rav Oshaya, אטו כולהו בחדא מחתא
מחתינהו? Atu kulhu b'chada machta machtinhu? That's a common phrase. He says,
what, you think they're all taught in the same bundle? Meaning, you
think just because you said one thing you can apply it like
across the board? It's not everything has the same ruling. היכא דאתמר
אתמר היכא דלא אתמר לא אתמר. Heicha d'itmar itmar heicha d'lo itmar
lo itmar. Where it was
said, it was said. Where it wasn't said, it wasn't said. So
one type of a tube was okay because it's common. This type
of a tube is not normal. is an aberration and it's a
problem. Now again it's not exactly clear why is it a problem
because it's not like you can say an extra tube is like
a missing tube. There are no tubes, so רש"י *Rashi* seems to
indicate well but since it's between the stomachs, it's like something is
missing with one of the stomachs. It's like there's a hole in
the stomach. So that's also an extension of this idea of something
extra is like something missing. Okay, let's try to just get to
the משנה *Mishnah*, I know we're a little over, but העיד נתן
בר שילא *Heid Nassan bar Shila*, so רב נתן בר שילא *Rav
Nassan bar Shila* testifies, רב טבחיא דציפורי *Rav Tavchaya di'Tzippori*, רב
*Rav* who was the butcher of ציפורי *Tzippori* at least, לפני רבי
*lifnei Rebbi*, testified in front of, רב *Rav* testified, רב נתן בר
שילא *Rav Nassan bar Shila* who was the head butcher in ציפורי
*Tzippori* testified in front of רבי *Rebbi*. על שני בני מעיים היוצאים
מן הבהמה כאחד שהיא טרפה *Al shenei benei mei'ayim hayotzim min habeheimah
ke'echad shehi tereifah*. If the animal basically has two large, two rectums,
two large intestines that causes the waste to come out, then it's
a טרפה *tereifah*. Now that's actually quite interesting because if you remember
from before, certain problems with the, with the rectum actually the גמרא
*Gemara* said could be missing and could be holes in it and
not be a טרפה *tereifah*. But maybe the entire one missing would
be and if it has two it's a טרפה *tereifah*. וכנגדם בעוף
כשרה *Uk'negedam b'of kesherah*, but if it happened by a bird it's
kosher. במה דברים אמורים שיוצאים בשני מקומות *Bameh devarim amurim sheyotzim bishnei
mekomot*. That's if they exit in two separate places. If essentially that
there are two, you know, anuses. אבל יוצאים במקום אחד *Aval yotzim
bemakom echad*, if they exit in the same place וכלין עד כאצבע
*vekalyan ad ke'etzba* and they combine with and they're only now the
width of an אצבע *etzba*, they've joined, so then כשרה *kesherah*. That's
kosher. So פלגי בה רב אמי ורב אסי *palgi bah Rav Ami
ve'Rav Assi*. They debated what that meant. חד אמר *Chad amar*, הא
דהדרי וערבי *ha d'hadrei ve'arbei*, that they, that the two tubes inside
the animal connected before they got to the exit hole, and therefore
it's considered only one. וחד אמר *Ve'chad amar*, אף על גב דלא
הדרי וערבי *af al gav d'lo hadrei ve'arbei*, even if they did
not connect inside the animal and they exited separately. So בשלמא למאן
דאמר *bishlama leman d'amar*, הא דהדרי וערבי *ha d'hadrei ve'arbei*, the tubes
connected in the animal, היינו דתניא עד כאצבע *hainu d'tanya ad ke'etzba*,
that when they actually come out they're only an אצבע *etzba* width
and they're essentially one tube. אלא למאן דאמר *Ella leman d'amar*, אף
על גב דלא הדרי וערבי *af al gav d'lo hadrei ve'arbei*, even
if they didn't reconnect inside of the animal, מאי עד כאצבע *mai
ad ke'etzba*, what does it mean it's only an אצבע *etzba*? So
it means עד כאצבע מלמטה *ad ke'etzba milmata*. It means that it
doesn't go, they're side by side and they come out in two
separate holes right next to each other, but they don't go, they're
not one below the other. So they're, so they don't go the,
the height of them is only an אצבע *etzba*, but they come
out right next to each other. Okay, so we'll have to pick
up tomorrow, but there we have the important principle of extra is
like it is missing which caused endless problems for the ראשונים *Rishonim*.